Guide to the Civil War Stereographs 1861-1865 PR 65-1
New-York Historical Society
Civil War Stereographs
1861-1865
New-York Historical Society
PR 65-1
5 Linear feet 868 items, within Stereograph File
The Civil War stereographs cover the entire period of the Civil War, from the first Battle of Bull Run through the surrender at Appomattox, and the triumphant parade of Union forces in Washington D.C. Most of the images were made in the Eastern Theatre, with scenes in Virginia by far in the majority. The Civil War Stereographs are digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
Photographer Mathew Brady is represented, as well as his former employees Alexander Gardner, James Gibson, and Timothy O'Sullivan, who set up their own firm in 1863 because they wanted credit for their work which had previously all appeared under Brady's name. Other photographers include George N. Barnard, who photographed in Virginia and the Carolinas, Sam A. Cooley, who was the "Official Photographer" for the 10th Army Corps, and local photographers from Richmond, Gettysburg and other locations.
Scope and Contents Note
The Civil War stereographs cover the entire period of the Civil War, from the first Battle of Bull Run through the surrender at Appomattox, and the triumphant parade of Union forces in Washington D.C. Most of the images were made in the Eastern Theatre, with scenes in Virginia by far in the majority. Views in northern states include naval shipyards in Massachusetts and Philadelphia, the battlefield at Gettysburg, and a rally and parades in New York City. Compelling images of death on the battlefield, and the destruction of cities, railroads and bridges show the devastating effects of the war. Individual and group portraits of participants are included along with images of soldiers relaxing in camps, drilling in the field, and ready for attack in trenches and other fortifications. There are images of African Americans fleeing slavery by crossing the Union lines, and of African Americans on southern plantations as well as serving in the Army and Navy. The damage to the Monitor after her fight with the Merrimac is shown, along with ships on the James River. Civilians also appear in the photographs, including photographers, artists and journalists, as well as a battlefield thief and members of the Sanitary Commission.
Most of the views presented here were published during the war by the photographers who made them, or by publishers such as E. & H.T. Anthony. Anthony's file was later obtained by General Ordway and published under successive imprints by John C. Taylor, and Taylor & Huntington to take advantage of the 25th anniversary of the war, and reunions that were held at the time.
The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online via New York Heritage.
Arrangement Note
Arranged geographically when know, otherwise arranged by subject. Stereographs are further arranged by photographer or publisher's name.
Provenance
The Society acquired these items from various sources, although primarily from George T. Bagoe (1886?-1948) who specialized in collecting Civil War stereographs among other subjects. His collection came to N-YHS in 1960 and 1961. Other significant groups of views were acquired in 1922, 1923 and 1936.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital copies are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Afro-Americans; Albumen prints; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Armies -- Officers; Confederate States of America; Georgia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; New York (State) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Parades; Soldiers; Stereographs; Portraits; Tennessee -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Battlefields.; South Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Campaigns.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Naval operations.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Destruction and pillage; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Transportation; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Military life; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Military facilities; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Medical care; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Casualties; Brady, Mathew B., -- 1823 (ca.)-1896, -- photographer; Confederate States of America. Army; Cooley, Sam A. (Samuel A.), photographer; E. & H.T. Anthony (Firm), publisher; Gardner, Alexander, -- 1821-1882, -- photographer; Gibson, James F., b. 1821, photographer; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1883--Portraits; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 -- Portraits; McClellan, George Brinton, 1826-1865--Portraits; O'Sullivan, Timothy, 1840-1882, photographer; Roche, T. C., photographer; United States Sanitary Commission.; United States of America. Army; Taylor & Huntington, publisher; Soule, John P., photographer; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891--Portraits; Anderson Gallery (Richmond, Va.); Barnard, George N., 1819-1902
- NOTE: This list provides an item-level description of each of the Civil War stereographs by item number. These stereographs are part of the larger Stereograph Collection and are housed in boxes 71-75.
- 1st Delaware, 12th New Jersey and 14th Connecticut at Stonewall, U.S.A., ca. 1880 (Item 771-1)
  General note
  Stereograph of a painting showing men engaged in battle.
- Field telegraph station., ca. 1861-ca.1865, published later (Item 771-2)
  Men seated under make-shift tent around telegraph equipment.
- Intelligent contrabands at leisure, November, 1863. (Item 772-1)
  Two African-American men seated outside of tent.
- A group of "contrabands.", ca.1861-ca.1865, published later (Item 772-2)
  Large group of African-American men, women, and children seated in front of a wooden structure.
- A Negro family coming into the Union lines., ca.1861-ca.1865, published later (Item 772-3)
  An African-American family around, and seated in, a covered wagon.
- [Group of soldiers, woman, and child in front of log building with sign reading "Union 17" hanging over doorway.], ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-1)
  Group of soldiers, woman, and child in front of log building with "Union 17" sign hanging over doorway.
- [Soldiers of the 7th Regiment New York Militia outside tent.], ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-2)
  Soldiers of the 7th New York State Militia relaxing outside tent.
- [Soldiers of the 7th Regiment New York State Militia.], ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-3)
  Soldiers of the 7th Regiment New York State Militia and an African- American man relaxing outside the tent labeled "The-Ruins."
- [Soldiers lounging around artillery emplacements.], ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-4)
  Soldiers lounging around artillery emplacements at possibly at Fort Jackson, La.
- [Officer and African-America man seated outside a camouflaged tent.], ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-5)
  Officer and African-America man seated outside tent camouflaged with brush and small trees.
- [Man standing next to tree with post office and other wood frame buildings in the background.], ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-6)
  Man standing next to tree with post office and other wood frame buildings in the background.
- Camp life, Army of the Potomac. Basking in the sunshine., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-7)
  Soldiers relaxing outside tents.
- Gymnastic field sports of the gallant 7th. A four story pile of men., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-8)
  Pyramid of soldiers in a field, others looking on.
- Camp life, Army of the Potomac. News from home., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-9)
  Four soldiers sitting outside a tent preparing food and reading a letter.
- Improvised dinner table in the field., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-10)
  Hand-colored view of a group of soldiers sitting around make-shift dining table with drums and flag hanging from the trees in the background.
- A Camp in a pleasant grove., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-11)
  Group portrait of soldiers and African-American boy seated in front of tent.
- Camp dinner., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-12)
  Hand-colored view of soldiers and African-American man sitting around a dinner table eating.
- The Way they cook dinner in camp., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-13)
  Four soldiers cooking dinner on small stoves beneath a tarp.
- Tent life of the 31st Pennsylvania regiment, ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-14)
  Soldiers with women and children outside of tents with personal belongings scattered around the camp site.
- A Group of soldiers of the 31st Pennsylvania Regiment., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-15)
  Group portrait of five soldiers with guns and swords.
- Capt. Bollerman's kitchen. Tasting the soup., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 773-16)
  Soldiers, a woman, and an African-American man relaxing while one soldier ceremoniously tastes the soup.
- View from the breastworks outside Fort Burnham, late Rebel Fort Harrison. Rebel pickets in the woods; a rebel fort in the middle distance., 1864 (Item 773-17)
  View from the Breastworks outside Fort Burnham, formerly the Confederate Fort Harrison, showing tents and buildings of rebel camp beyond.
- [Tents of Camp Winfield Scott in the distance.], 1862 (Item 773-18)
  Tents of Camp Winfield Scott in the distance.
- [Soldiers caring for horses at camp.], 1862 (Item 773-19)
  Soldiers caring for horses at camp.
- [Covered wagons and horses on a hill side with tents in the far background, Camp Winfield Scott, Va.], 1862 (Item 773-20)
  Covered wagons and horses on a hill side with tents in the far background, Camp Winfield Scott, Va.
- Commissary department, headquarters Army Potomac, April, 1864. (Item 773-21)
  Soldiers of the Commissary Dept. butchering meat, carcasses hanging from a pole, left, barrels of supplies, right.
- Winter quarters of telegraphic and photographic departments, attached to headquarters Army Potomac, April, 1864. (Item 773-22)
  Soldier on what appears to be a swing set among pine trees, tents and log buildings in background, one possibly O'Sullivan's darkroom.
- Rear view of winter quarters of telegraphic and photographic departments, attached to headquarters Army Potomac, April, '64., 1864 (Item 773-23)
  Men, including an African-American man, standing outside log buildings with a wagon to the right.
- Headquarters Army of the Potomac, eastern half of camp, April, '64., 1864 (Item 773-24)
  Partiality cleared field with tents in the background.
- Camp of the 114th Pennsylvania Volunteer Regiment, April, 1864. (Item 773-25)
  Soldiers in formation out in an open field with tents in the background.
- A Breakfast party at headquarters, Army Potomac, April, 1864. (Item 773-26)
  Officers seated outside a tent enjoying a meal, young African American man standing by.
- Discussing the probabilities of the next advance., 1862 (Item 773-27)
  Two men seated smoking pipes with horses in the background, possibly the photographers Timothy O'Sullivan and Alexander Gardner.
- Group at transportation office, Aquia Creek, February, 1863. (Item 773-28)
  Two men outside transportation tent with sign reading Transportation Office, Subsistence and Stores, Capt. F.C. Tripter, AAQM.
- Headquarters New York Herald in Army of the Potomac, Sept., 1863. (Item 773-29)
  Journalists relaxing outside of tents set among trees, wagon with "N.Y.H. Headquarters" painted on the side to the right.
- Group at Telegraphic Corps quarters, headquarters Army Potomac., 1863 (Item 773-30)
  Men, possibly journalists seated around a table eating and drinking.
- Group, Comte de Paris, Duc de Chartres, Prince de Joinville, and friends, Camp Winfield Scott, near Yorktown, May 1, 1862. (Item 773-31)
  French nobles and others seated around table eating and drinking.
- Group, Prince's servants., 1862 (Item 773-32)
  Four menservants preparing a meal, or cleaning.
- Officers of the 60th New York Volunteers at Sulphur Springs, Virginia., 1862 (Item 773-33)
  Eleven soldiers seated for a group portrait with other military men and a springhouse in the background.
- Officers of the 60th New York Volunteers at Sulphur Springs, Virginia., 1862 (Item 773-34)
  Fourteen officers posing for group portrait.
- Camp of Gen'l M'Dowell's body guard, July 5, 1862. (Item 773-35)
  Soldiers seated underneath a tree with tents and a house in the background.
- Field telegraph, battery wagon and officers tent of military Telegraph Corps, headquarters Army of the Potomac, 24th June, 1864. (Item 773-36)
  Telegraph wagon and tent with the operators outside of the tent.
- 7th Regiment (N.G.) N.Y.S.T., Camp Cameron, Washington City, Tent No. 20, Co. 2, May 1861. (Item 773-37)
  5 soldiers seated outside of tent.
- Mounting Guard., 1864, published later (Item 773-38)
  Groups of soldiers from the 114th Pennsylvania Infantry standing in formation.
- Mounting Guard., ca. 1861-ca. 1865, published later (Item 773-39)
- Mounting Guard., 1864, published later (Item 773-40)
- 1st Massachusetts Cavalry camp in the woods., ca. 1861-ca. 1865, published later (Item 773-41)
  View of companies "C" and "D," 1st Massachusetts Cavalry in front of their tents.
- Filling their canteens., 1861-1865, published later (Item 773-42)
  Canvas covered well being used by soldiers to replenish their canteens.
- Filling their canteens., 1861-1865, published later (Item 773-43)
- Camp in Monument Garden, Chattanooga., ca. 1863, published later (Item 773-44)
  Soldiers relaxing in a field with log structures in the background.
- Dr. Richard Burr, Embalming Surgeon, Army of the James., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 774-1)
  Doctor embalming dead soldier.
- He sleeps his last sleep. A Confederate soldier who after being wounded had evidently dragged himself to a little ravine on the hill side, where he died., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 774-2)
  Dead Confederate soldier lying in a field.
- Members of a South Carolina Regiment laid out for burial., 1863 (Item 774-3)
  Members of a South Carolina Regiment laid out for burial with identifying markers.
- Graves of Union prisoners at the Race Course., 1865 (Item 774-4)
  Graves with markers in open field with a building in the background.
- Embalming building in the field, Army of the James, before Richmond. A great many bodies of the slain are embalmed here, preparatory to sending them North for burial., 1861-1865, published later (Item 774-5)
  Embalming building in the field, large shed, hung round with curtains and with signs for Doctor Bunnel.
- Embalming building in the field, Army of the James, before Richmond. A great many bodies of the slain are embalmed here, preparatory to sending them North for burial., ca.1861-ca.1865, published later (Item 774-6)
- Execution of a colored soldier., 1861-1865, published later (Item 774-7)
  African-American soldier hanged for attempted rape.
- Execution of a colored soldier., 1861-1865, published later (Item 774-8)
- Frank L. Keyes, wounded soldier, July 1862. (Item 775-1)
  Wounded soldier in bed with a woman seated at the bed side, flag hanging on wall.
- The ever welcome Sanitary Commission., 1861-1865, published later (Item 775-2)
  United States Sanitary Commission covered wagon with horses and soldiers in front of a fort, large flag overhead.
- The ever welcome Sanitary Commission., 1861-1865, published later (Item 775-3)
- Scene on board a frigate, ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-1)
  Two sailors standing on deck of a ship.
- [Large ship on a body of water.], ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-2)
  Large ship on a body of water.
- Turret of Monitor, "Terror.", ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-3)
  Turret of Monitor, "Terror" at Philadelphia Navy Yard.
- Quarter deck of the U.S. Steamer "Tallapoosa" [sic] Capt. De Haven., after Sept. 1864 (Item 776-4)
  Group of sailors and officers on deck of Talapoosa, with cannon.
- Monitor Terror, Philadelphia., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-5)
  Monitor Terror, Philadelphia.
- The captured Ram Atlanta, in James River., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-6)
  Looking at the Atlanta over an expanse of water.
- Monitor Cononicus, on the James River, taking in coal., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-7)
  Monitor Cononicus, on the James River, taking in coal.
- Monitor Cononicus, on the James River, taking in Coal., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-8)
- Gunboat Mendota at Deep Bottom, James River., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-9)
  Two-masted and side-wheeled Gunboat Mendota at Deep Bottom, James River.
- Double turreted Monitor Onondaga, on the James River., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-10)
  Sailors seated in rowboat near shore with the "Onondaga," flag on stern, in the distance.
- Gunboat Mendota on the James River near Dutch Gap., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-11)
  Gunboat Mendota on the James River near Dutch Gap.
- Monitor "Casco," James River, Va., near Dutch Gap., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-12)
  Monitor "Casco," James River, Va., near Dutch Gap.
- Gun boats on the James River, Va., above Varina Landing., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-13)
  Various ships seen from the shore of the James River above Varina Landing.
- After deck and turret of Monitor Kaatskill. Taken at Charleston Harbor, S.C., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-14)
  Sailors and officers on the Monitor Kaatskill, cannons and lifeboats on deck.
- The Teazer [sic] Confederate gunboat, captured by the Maritanza [sic]. July 4, 1862. This view shows the destruction caused by the bursting of 100 pound rifled shell. (Item 776-15)
  The Teaser, a Confederate gunboat captured by the Maratanza, July 4, 1862, with gapping hole in the deck and other damage.
- Group, officers on board the Monitor, July 9,1862. (Item 776-16)
  Group portrait of officers on board the Monitor, July 9,1862.
- Deck view of the iron-clad gunboat Galena, showing the effect of the fire from Fort Darling., 1862 (Item 776-17)
  Deck view of the iron-clad gunboat Galena, showing the effect of the fire from Fort Darling.
- Group on board the Monitor, July 9, 1862. (Item 776-18)
  Sailors on the deck of the Monitor, including African American in the foreground, July 6, 1862.
- [Monitors at Charlestown Navy Yard.] (Item 776-19)
  Two boats docked at what may be Charlestown Navy Yard.
- Monitors, Charlestown Navy Yard. (Item 776-20)
  Two monitors docked at Charlestown Navy Yard, skyline in background.
- U.S. Frigate "Pensacola" off Alexandria, Va., 1861, published later (Item 776-21)
  Sailors sitting on shore looking at the U.S. Frigate "Pensacola" off Alexandria, Va.
- Hundred-pounder gun on rebel steamer., 1862, published later (Item 776-22)
  Hundred-pound rifle-gun on the Rebel blockade-runner Teaser captured by the United States gun-boat Maratanza, July 4,1862.
- Effect of Yankee shell on the "Teazer." [sic], 1862, published later (Item 776-23)
  The Rebel blockade-runner "Teaser" was captured by the United States Gunboat "Maratanza, " July 4, 1862. This view shows a portion of the deck of the "Teaser," and the destruction from shells hitting the deck.
- The original "Monitor" after her fight with the "Merrimac.", 1862, published later (Item 776-24)
  Part of the deck and turret of the "Monitor;" near the port-hole can be seen the dents made by the heavy steel-pointed shot from the guns of the "Merrimac," officers to the right.
- The original "Monitor" after her fight with the "Merrimac.", 1862, published later (Item 776-25)
- Iron-clad gunboat "Galena," showing the effect of Rebel shot., ca. 1861-ca. 1865, published later (Item 776-26)
  This is a view of the United States gunboat "Galena" after her flight with Fort Darling on Drewey's Bluff, James River, in July, 1862, looking along the hull with guns showing in the ports, sailors on deck.
- Double-turret monitor "Onondaga" in the James River., ca.1861-ca.1865, published later (Item 776-27)
  Sailors seated in row boat near shore with the "Onondaga" in the distance.
- The Rebel ram "Atlanta.", ca.1861-ca.1865, published later (Item 776-28)
  Looking across the water at the Rebel ram "Atlanta."
- Gunboat "Mendota," in James River, near Deep Bottom, 1864., 1864, published later (Item 776-29)
  Gunboat "Mendota," in James River, near Deep Bottom, 1864.
- U.S. Steamer "Massasoit," in James River, 1864., 1864, published later (Item 776-30)
  Sailors seated on a dock with the steamer Massasoit in the background.
- Admiral Dahlgren and staff on the "Pawnee.", ca.1861-ca.1965, published later (Item 776-31)
  Rear Admiral John Dahlgren and staff on the deck of the "Pawnee" off Charleston, S.C.
- Smoke-stack of the Rebel Ram "Virginia.", ca.1861-ca.1865, published later (Item 776-32)
  The smoke-stack of the Rebel Ram "Virginia" filled with holes, and laying on a beach.
- Broadside deck view of monitor "Dictator.", ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 776-33)
  Officers, sailors, and others aboard the "Dictator."
- Special artist of Harper's Weekly sketching battle field of Gettysburg., 1863 (Item 777-1)
  Artist Alfred R. Waud, seated with his sketchbook.
- A battle-field Vulture, Godfor by name, one of those inhuman creatures who follow in the wake of armies, robbing the field of blankets, clothing, turning the pockets of the dead, etc., copyright 1886 (Item 777-2)
  Portrait of man in dirty clothing.
- Jim Kerrigan, the "mollie" squealer., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 777-3)
  Man in civilian clothing seated in front of brick wall.
- Group, Messrs. Allen, Hammond, Fargo, and Hall., 1862 (Item 777-4)
  Five gentlemen posed for a group portrait; man standing at left appears to be Lincoln; "Allen" is Allan Pinkerton, head of the Secret Service.
- A rare old third dimension portrait of Abraham Lincoln, made in the days of the Civil War., ca.1861-ca.1865, published later (Item 778-1)
  Abraham Lincoln seated with arm resting on a table.
- Abraham Lincoln., ca.1861-ca.1865, published later (Item 778-2)
  Bust portrait of Abraham Lincoln.
- [Abraham Lincoln standing outside a tent with officer and another man, possibly Allan Pinkerton.], ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 778-3)
  Abraham Lincoln standing outside a tent with officer and another man, possibly Allan Pinkerton.
- Lincoln at Antietam Oct. 3rd, 1862, with Gen. McClellan and staff. (Item 778-4)
  Officers, including General McClellan, with Lincoln outside tent at Antietam.
- Lincoln visits General McClellan at Antietam., 1862 (Item 778-5)
  Lincoln and General McClellan in his tent at Antietam, table draped with American flag.
- President Lincoln and Gen. McClellan in McClellan's tent., 1862, published later (Item 778-6)
- Gen. Robert Anderson (Major at Sumter), ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 779-1)
  Portrait of General Robert Anderson, Major at Fort Sumter.
- Group, Gen'ls Barry, Slocum, Newton, Franklin, and friends, May 14, 1862. (Item 779-2)
  Group portrait of Union generals, child seated in the foreground.
- Capt. Bates' quarters, headquarters 3d Army Corps, Army Potomac, April, 1864. (Item 779-3)
  Capt. Bates seated outside small log building.
- General Benj. F. Butler and staff., ca. 1861-1865 (Item 779-4)
  General Butler and staff in dress uniforms, civilians in the background.
- Col. Corcoran and staff, of the gallant 69th., ca.1861-ca.1863 (Item 779-5)
  Officers standing outside a tent.
- Brig. Gen. Crawford and staff., ca.1861-ca.1865 (Item 779-6)